[Music]
when there's increased volatility in the
market there's more opportunity to make
more money if you play it right then
when the market has less volatility and
similarly when there's just increased
volatility and say geopolitics as a
whole there's more ability for more
significant grabs of power than there
are when things are more equilibria and
so the saying never let a good crisis go
to waste
sometimes crises are just completely
made-up right they're false flagged
sometimes they're not false flagged but
they are they just naturally emerge and
then some agents are more focused to see
how they can advance the agendas they
already had utilizing the dynamics of
that situation rather than try to fix
the situation so let's say for instance
that I was one of the many people that
got good intelligence back in early
January about what was happening in
Wuhan and how many people five to seven
million people left who hung before
quarantine and that they got on planes
not to the rest of China but to the rest
of the world and what was likely to
happen from that so we see some senators
that sold stock in January right but
that's a small part like those are
formal intelligence briefings to people
who have classified access but the
private intelligence agencies largely
work for hedge funds and financial
institutions and things like that and
they're looking at the same information
so if I run a hedge fund and I see that
there's a situation that could have
meaningful downturn to the economy but I
can make money when the economy goes
down
and we're already at the top of a you
know a stock market that's probably
about as high as it can be because the
underlying economy is actually very
unhealthy right the total percent of GDP
that's going to debt servicing is
unsustainably high the wealth inequality
is unsustainably disparate it's
basically a power-law distribution you
have a few companies that make up most
of the success of the stock market
because it's cap-weighted and then
almost everything else pretty profoundly
lagging you have a totally unsustainable
amount of total debt and all of that's
resulted in the need for ongoing
quantitative easing and a negative
yielding bond market and totally weird
stuff with that right and so the markets
not going to keep going up and staying
that high forever anyways and so being
able to have that foreknowledge and say
now is a good time to sell these stocks
and by the way let's actually short a
bunch of stuff to make money as the
market goes excuse me
to make money as the market goes down
and then the value is gonna get really
low if if airlines can't fly the price
of airlines is gonna get really low but
airlines are a real thing the world's
gonna need the value of that sense of
kind of evaporate so being able to buy
it up at hugely discounted prices before
it goes back up is pretty awesome
opportunity to consolidate power and
let's say that I have large pools of
liquid capital and I haven't so I'm a
family office or sovereign wealth fund
it has been hard to deploy that capital
very effectively for a while because
I've got negative interest yielding you
know bond markets I can't just make
interest by sitting on it and you know
there hasn't been huge volatility of the
type that could be very effective and
market stock market prices were high but
now you can deploy that capital very
effectively by being able to buy up real
valuable utilities at a very discounted
price also if I am interested in
increased surveillance capitalism or
increased surveillance state or just
concentration of power of any kind when
things get worse people become more
willing to accept solutions that have
some consequences and so I don't even
have to do anything to make it bad I
simply have to not make it better say
we're working on it and bureaucracies
are slow until we get to the position
that we actually have the capability to
do something and so and if I'm trying to
advance a geopolitical agenda and I
really want an alliance with these
countries who are currently allied
somewhere else and I can just to help
the situation break those alliances like
all of those types of things
I'm not saying anyone did anything I'm
saying that these are reasonable things
to understand that there's an incentive
landscape for right now someone who
people who own hedge funds or large
pools of capital they had the
intelligence of what was happening could
they if they wanted to maximally help
and you know try to start engaging
solutions and trying to use some of that
money to influence governments to say
hey let's actually put these travel bans
on sooner and let's start getting tests
gets rolled out and PPE distributed and
etc of course they could and they can
say it's not their job and it's not
their job right their job is to maximize
return for the assets under management
for their shareholders which they do a
very good job of do I think that's a
conspiracy do I think they intended the
virus no but I think that their
incentive is to do predatory opportunism
more than it is to solve the problem
I think the vast majority of what we're
seeing is just predatory opportunism I
don't think it's all just that and so if
you think about the power law
distribution of wealth you have a few
actors who have really just a small
number like if you look at the House of
Saud and the House of Rothschild and
Putin's personal wealth it's kind of
like way above everybody else's right
and then you've got like a small but
larger said of a hundred billionaire's
and and then it you know kind of Falls
deeply in the same way that there is a
power-law distribution and wealth
there's a power-law distribution in
geopolitical power and in hybrid warfare
power and so the few actors that have
the most asymmetric capacity habit by
being good at gaining and maintaining
asymmetric capacity they didn't get it
by like lottery right and so to think
that the actors that have the most
asymmetric capacity have it for any
reason other than they're the best at
gaining asymmetric capacity is naive and
[Music]
so do those actors have more ability to
influence the overall landscape to
continue to advance asymmetric power
yeah is it guaranteed what will happen
no it's a high stakes kind of situation
so if someone could ask I'm not gonna
say anything here it's not relevant
about specific actors but what I can say
is if you have any actors that you are
curious about you just say okay let's
make a list starting in whenever
starting in November or December of the
things that the w-h-o said
or the CDC said or whatever group you
want to look at or President Trump or
whomever and say look at the things that
they said in the things that they did
chronologically in time relative to what
would have actually been the right thing
to do and made sense and then just look
at the Delta between those and then just
try to explain the Delta some of it
totally might be incompetence some of it
totally might be bureaucracy just look
at does it does that seem to account for
all of it I mean there are very basic
examples the w-h-o was telling people
not to wear PPE until not that long ago
and Trump was saying this we've got this
solved this isn't a big deal until it
was almost overwhelming US cities right
and Chuck Beijing shut down flights from
ohan to the rest of China but didn't
shut down flights from ohan to the rest
of the world there are a bunch of
studies that are in process by major
public health organizations that are
looking at the drugs that are currently
interesting the antivirals but only
doing late-stage trials of the
antivirals particularly of antivirals
that are generic so there's a there's
one particular study that is looking at
hydroxychloroquine late-stage with
vitamin C as the placebo I'm not gonna
say which group it is but it's easy to
find out vitamin C is not a placebo
vitamin C is extremely well established
for having antiviral benefits actually
even in late stage more than most
pharmaceuticals do and one can expect
that late stage wouldn't be effective
anyways so maybe that's just a dumb
study maybe it's just a badly designed
study but if I wanted to say look Trump
was an idiot or I wanted to say see this
generic drug we can't make any money on
doesn't work so this other drug or
vaccine
we have is the only option and so I
wanted to have a particular result come
out looking like science but it's
actually not science because it's
science being set up to produce a
particular result I would consider that
info warfare pretending to be science is
it that or not I can say if I wanted to
do info warfare I would do it that way
so just because something is a
randomized control trial done by a
prestigious university does it mean that
it's good information no this is a very
important topic
[Music]
now here's another important topic
legitimate Authority legitimate
Authority very powerful thing right
because if there is something that seems
like a source of legitimate Authority
that can decide what policy should be or
control public opinion then the power of
that is such that any group that is
seeking the power to influence policy or
control public opinion would have
maximum incentive to try to influence
that legitimate Authority and so we have
no problem seeing this in retrospect
right we have no problem seeing the way
that priestly Authority during the
Middle Ages was very influenced by the
kings and banks and whatever that we're
all basically playing different aspects
of power games and so whether we're
talking about a legitimate Authority
that comes from a religious source or a
science source or a one thing that you
learn about science and this was this is
kind of a postmodern of critique but not
quite because there there's a more
earnest way to take it the more complex
this physical system the easier it is to
very different answers based on how you
set up the study and so the larger the
data set is the easier it is to
cherry-pick data that supports whatever
I want where it's actually not lying
it's just cherry-picked but similarly if
I'm looking at
something as complex as a cell or a body
there's no way I can test everything
that is relevant to that thing right so
I can say well this particular biometric
went up and that's a measure of health
there might be plenty of other
biometrics that also went up that are
measures of illness or that went down
that are measures of health but where
they aren't even things that we look at
in the study and so I can do info
warfare very well with complexity
because I can say what is the thing that
I want to say to advance whatever the
narrative or the agenda is and I can
make something that looks like science
that says that thing so just just
because something looks like science can
you trust that it is true no you
actually really have to look at the
preponderance of data you have to look
at how the methodology was done you have
to look at who funded it
you've got like there's a lot of things
and as the situation gets more complex
the more so so basic physical chemistry
inside of a beaker or how a transistor
works is very very different than how a
cell works now does that mean that all
authorities are run by lizard people to
install 5g nanobots and think as part of
the AI matrix no it doesn't mean that
and that's one of the other things is
people jump to kind of maximally
paranoid pattern-matching
do I think that SARS co2 is a virus
meaning a actual physical infectious
agent that is not just the result of bio
terrain or somebody's own endogenous
exosome when it's exposed to 5g or
something like that yes I think it is a
virus and I think that it's very well
established if you we have been able to
actually look at the shape and structure
of the virus and lots of different
universities independently and in
samples from people and whatever and
compare it to other coronaviruses and to
Sarris Cove one and to look at how it
would have evolved into being in the
relationship with bats and other things
do I think that 5g causes coronavirus no
do I think people who have covin
symptoms are really some other thing
caused by 5g no the lope if you do look
at a map of the distribution of 5g and a
map of the distribution of SARS or of
excuse me of Cove in nineteen they don't
match there are areas that have 5g that
were not terribly hit and their areas
that were terribly hit that don't have
5g so I saw a number of studies that
rolled out but not studies like memes
they rolled out that said look here the
places that were hit and these were all
a month after 5g was installed or the
first place have typed year whatever and
they were just actually wrong like when
I went and looked at it they there was
some pretty compelling so I'm like wow
if that's true it was not true and so
this is just like basic fact-checking
do I think that there are companies that
are extremely powerful companies that
are extremely focused on rolling 5g out
yes I think Huawei and Verizon in
particular some other ones have very
deep investment in 5g do I think that
the safety of it is well enough
established to roll it out no but I
think that on some of the previous
wireless communication - and I also
think it on the cumulative load of the
total thing so the fact that it's not
ionizing radiation is not the only
relevant saying yes that means that it's
not like acutely causing you cancer like
a microwave but it's signals
transmitting signal does
is signal transmission something that's
happening in your brain and between
cells that is a part of how the
communication of a biological organism
works yes is there is it reasonable to
think that there could be interference
yeah
should it be on the burden of the
activists to prove that it's unsafe or
the burden of the telecom companies to
prove that it's safe before being rolled
out the burden of proof should
absolutely be on proving safety do we
need it
no we don't need it well we need it for
the economy to grow know the gibberish
do we need it because we need an IOT
connected smart city world that fast no
do we like fast shit and like we want to
get to self-driving cars whatever yeah
we totally do now is 5g based on the
frequency bands and everything going to
be more dangerous or not than 4G haven't
done the studies I haven't to know I can
say that just intuitively I have
concerns about it and I believe that
once it's rolled out it'll be impossible
to do proper studies because you won't
be able to isolate it anymore
you won't be able to get to environments
where it's not without changing your
whole life so much so you've changed
enough other variables that you can't
say like oh yes when you're in the
Arctic Circle your health issues change
but was that because now you're in a
pristine environment air wise or water
wise or different sun or and so I think
I would much rather that we were doing
the right kinds of safety studies up
front that weren't only looking at acute
effects but chronic effects this is
something that I'm very upset about our
entire medical paradigm is the topic of
toxicity in general and deficiency of
nutrients and pathogenicity in terms of
infection we don't look at chronic
subclinical issues
so we have a clinical definition of okay
here is you have a you have a clinical
vitamin D deficiency right you you've
got rickets well here's the level of
rickets or you you have a clinical
vitamin C deficiency you have scurvy
well pretty much nobody gets Kerby right
like you have to be in some fucked up
food situation you get scurvy which is
why there are still a lot of kind of
mainstream doctors who say you don't
need supplements and nobody really needs
vitamin C or vitamin D or whatever this
but then you have what is the optimal
level for human thriving and the
healthiest people with the healthiest
diets and there's a pretty big range
between the optimal level and scurvy and
if you're here your Doc's are gonna say
you're not deficient but you might
actually be and but the deficiency means
you are now acutely dying right you are
in an acute death process directly
related to this one identifiable thing
but above that you might be in a you
will probably live less long and have
increased susceptibility to different
kinds of diseases but you'll never be
able to track it to this because it's
your sub clinical level of vitamin C
plus a vitamin D plus of a bunch of
other things plus of toxicities plus of
whatever right is basically just sub
optimal dynamics that support overall
system homeo dynamics when we're looking
if we're only looking at does this cause
an immediate acute one for one thing to
be able to say this was a necessary and
sufficient cause of a disease that's
just a broken model which is why I think
in modern medicine were quite good at
solving acute causation things if
someone gets an acute poisoning or an
acute injury or an acute infection we're
actually pretty good at that but when it
comes to complex chronic illness
autoimmune disease neurodegenerative
disease psychiatric disease we don't
have much in the way of real cures for
those things we have symptomatic
treatments and we have things that can
stop certain parts of the disease
pathology progression that's because it
doesn't have a single cause and the
cause the many causes aren't even the
same ones are different causes and
different people and they're very
delayed in time so there's a whole new
model
it's needed for that but if I'm doing
safety studies looking for a near term
cause which I would always if I am a
company wanting to advance something I
don't want to be testing something for
30 years I don't want to be looking at
the long term all cause mortality
associated with the things so there's a
very real question of how do we advance
like how do we advance new things where
the negative effects might be very
causally delayed but then this is where
we also have to think about risk and
necessity and things like that so do I
think that the safety studies that are
done are based on the wrong model of
safety yes I think it's the wrong model
of safety now do I think that there is a
that 5g is a mind control system to kind
of brown noise everybody's mind and to
activate vaccine implanted nano chips
and whatever I've never I mean it's an
interesting idea if there was any group
that was actually that well coordinated
and powerful that would also be kind of
interesting I have never seen any
evidence that is compelling when I
followed some of those rabbit holes that
the evidence that I have been able to
find is not compelling that doesn't mean
it's not true right I'm not closing the
door on that's for sure not true maybe
there are reptilians running shit but I
have no evidence to believe so and it
seems exceedingly
something that's actually a very
interesting thing to do is to look at
declassified documents of things that
were conspiracy theories in the past and
now we actually know happen because the
documents got Declassified and so you
know there were several in the Vietnam
area the Gulf of Tonkin is a very famous
one but also the firing torpedoes into
the water and saying that we had sank
Vietnamese ships to increase the
escalation for the war and things about
operation Mockingbird Operation
Paperclip COINTELPRO there's like
there's a number of things that are now
Declassified because those people all
died and we're during the time that it
was still happening anyone who said
anything about it would be a conspiracy
nut and so and similarly when when the
USSR fell there was a bunch of
Declassified stuff that came out in
Baltic States I have a friend that runs
a private intelligence company who went
to Yugoslavia and pulled the
intelligence records then and looked at
the way that the KGB built their system
of DSM to be able to classify anything
that went against the state as a mental
illness and it was like very clearly
documented how they did it and the ideas
behind it and the whole thing about the
way that J Edgar Hoover was targeting
the Black Panthers not like that that
wouldn't have been known except that you
know people broke in and found the shit
right so does that stuff happen yeah of
course it happens and it happens in the
public sector meaning government
intelligence agencies you know military
it also happens in the private sector
right so for when you see the Enron type
things for every Enron there's a lot of
those that happen all the time they just
aren't caught and for every Madoff and
whatever
that said most of the common conspiracy
theories that I see are things that I
can't find any good grounding for and
they're like many of them tend to be far
more fantastical then just the kind of
typical social science of yes of course
groups with really big budgets probably
have more advanced tech than is publicly
known about and yes of course for
national security purposes some should
is kept secret and they're actually
engaged in war and preparation for war
and so and yes like the people that get
to the top of power stacks get there by
being good at getting to the top of
power stacks and that means a bunch of
things psychologically in the
disposition because there will be
sociopaths that will want to overturn
them and they will only not get
overturned by the draconian measures of
the sociopaths if they are better at
being able to play that game than they
are you know we can talk about
conspiracy as a function of the system
incentives right whatever it is the
system incentivizes creates a kind of
topology and the people just kind of
move within the shape of that topology
but then they in turn shape the topology
so there's a there's a reinforcing thing
and one of the problems is that like
sociopaths and sadists are a real thing
and people who are not that actually
have a hard time believing that because
they have empathy and they are
empathizing with what it must be like to
be someone else so they're getting wrong
they have a hard time putting themselves
in the position of someone who's inner
experiences is different from theirs as
it actually is but you know when you
look at cluster B disorders there's a
whole set of disorders that are oriented
to power and including abuses of power
so there are not one for one and perfect
not every time but statistical
correlation with
of high power and psychologies that are
oriented to who want that and that means
also differential an asymmetric power
meaning use increased power over others
to continue to grow and maintain
asymmetric power it's funny how easy it
is to see throughout history right like
when we're looking at Genghis Khan or
Alexander the Great or Napoleon or
whatever we're like oh yeah the those
guys just went and killed fucking
everybody right and yet then we look at
the people who are most powerful today
they're genetically the same kinds of
people who and we have a situation that
in some ways seems more civil but also
in some ways just because we hide it
better you know like we had a nice
Democrat and present presidency in the
US and we drone strike to a lot of
civilians and for very questionable
actual motives and and
factory farms are as gruesome as
anything that was done in the Dark Ages
at a massive scale that almost everybody
watching this is paying to make that
happen right so it's like oh I didn't
kill her I pay the hit man okay you
fucking paid to have the wet works done
well buying something comes from a
factory farm is that right you're like
paying someone else to do this kind of
gruesome what works and so the reason I
say this is because I want to see us
emerge into the higher angels of our
nature but we can only do that if we can
also face the reality of the total set
of things that the human experience does
and specifically some of the uglier
things that it does and the relationship
to power that ends up getting and now
one can also take that too far take that
as a general set of principles and
assume that everyone in a position of
power is a child eating say this
Satanist which would also be silly
and this is one of the things that I
find with regard to conspiracy is I find
that people have an aesthetic bias where
anything they hear as a conspiracy they
either just kind of reject it up front
off fucking tinfoil hat conspiracy
theorists they just automatically
without studying it even though history
shows how much people have conspired
just meaning some people share info with
each other to advance shared agendas
without sharing it with the public and
sharing some disinfo you can go back to
Sun Tzu and read about this info and how
to do this info right like we've been
doing that for a thousand years pretty
intelligently and coordinated Lee and so
it's interesting how easy it is for
people to reject something as oh that's
dumb conspiracy thinking when you
actually study history then on the other
hand there are people who if they hear
any conspiracy they assume it's probably
true and if they hear that anything came
from a authoritative institution they
assume it's probably corrupt and that's
also completely silly because if the
groups were that corrupt they would be
overturned like if they were that
completely in whole-cell corrupt or is a
there's a balance of that it's not just
evilness that gets them there it's also
effectiveness at a lot of things right
it is actually the ability to produce
and manage and do logistics and the
ability to win power games it's a mix of
those things right so is everything
coming out of a major university or
major institution or you know government
regulatory body a lying conspiracy no is
a lot of it at least highly influenced
yeah does that mean that most of the
people who are involved even no no of
course not most of the people involved
are just doing their job and they were
told to research this so they're doing a
good job of doing honest research on
this now the fact that they're
researching this as opposed to this and
that there's an agenda as to why to
research this as opposed to that they
will never even know that that agenda
what this means though is that almost
everyone lives in in a topology that is
you know like what do I do for job
protection there are certain things that
like there's stuff I'm not going to say
be
I'll lose my job there's certain stuff I
have to say and I have to do to just
keep my job I got to take care of my
family so whatever it is even if it
seems kind of unethical or asshole ish
or not the thing I'd most like to do
it's office policy or whatever so just
for job security and then for promotion
and for ladder climbing I am gonna do
the thing that's effective within that
space so basically the incentives and
the disincentives the topology of that
space is going to inform my action as a
average agent in that space but some
people have asymmetric influence on the
architecture of those topologies and so
one of the things that I think most
people don't think about enough is that
a relatively small amount of fairly
sociopathic people can create topologies
that lots of otherwise not sociopathic
people will participate in towards
relatively sociopathic results so let's
say that profit becomes a motive for war
if you study history again the idea that
that's a thing becomes pretty clear and
when you look at the size that
military-industrial complex is out of
the total economic bloc and the size of
the government contracts it gets
compared to other areas whenever the
fact that if the demand went away the
the profit of the supply side would go
away and it is actually the fiduciary
responsibility of all business owners to
continue to manufacture demand we can go
back and historically look at cases
right we can look at gulf of tonkin or
whatever where there were false flag
events for whatever motives so let's say
there's some fucked up motives that some
very small number of people have that
end up influencing other people and the
other people are not necessarily even
aware of what those motives are the
soldier who is in the battlefield isn't
fighting for financial interest who's
risking his life and making a relatively
low wage but he still might be doing
something that is when he is involved in
the in the bombing or the whatever
still might be killing civilians for
Wars it should never be fought and he
just doesn't even know that right so
he's engaged in an overall in activity
that we could call sociopathic activity
for non sociopathic reasons personally
and we can see the same thing in the
corporate world we can see the same
thing in all over the place this was the
SS troupe who were being tried in the
Nuremberg trials and how many of them
said no we actually didn't believe
everything we were doing was good it
started out with some ideological stuff
and then it got really fucked up and
then when they were asked did you tried
to stop no and they all repeated the
same German phrases that basically said
officers orders we didn't have a choice
and so this property by which so yes
there's somebody does a really fucked-up
thing they don't even make it obvious or
they have some fucked-up motives and
they create a set of office policies or
command and control policies or whatever
it is and everyone else just kind of
doing their job and they're even usually
told something that what they're doing
is valorous or good right scientists who
are told they're doing this for one
reason and then it is used for a
weaponized purpose inside of military or
whatever and then there's also that if
one actor is developing a new weapon all
the other actors have to develop the new
weapon plus counter weapons there's the
arms race side so both of those are the
situations in which bad actors are
capable of effecting a incentive
landscape that affects lots of other
actors one of the things we will need
for an effective civilization is a way
to be able to bind bad actors quickly
which will require that kind of
transparency to be able to identify that
it is actually bad acting when they're
seeking to dis inform which is this
question of true information versus
faulty information
a lot of people have a strong bias
towards wanting certainty which means
that they will adopt more certainty than
the epistemic that they went through
should warrant and this can be for
different reasons it's generally wanting
security and conflating security
uncertainty and and so recognizing how
big of an infinity the unknowable is
everyone has to make very deep friends
with uncertainty to not be mentally ill
that doesn't mean that they have to do
the move that all there is is
uncertainty nothing can possibly be
known which is also gibberish because
the fact that I can't know anything with
perfect certainty doesn't mean that I
can't know things with much higher
relative certainty based on certain
epistemic processes that inform right
action so do I want some kinds of trials
on my drugs before utilizing the drugs
as opposed to just pendulum dowsing or
guessing yes I did I definitely do and
are there certain kinds of processes
that will give increased certainty to be
able to inform certain types of actions
based on the consequent she ality of
those actions yes does any of that give
absolutely perfect certainty no because
I can't rule out unknown unknowns but I
can certainly say I have enough
certainty to inform right action here
and so people having a mature
relationship with certainty and
uncertainty is that they're not
uncomfortable with either there are a
lot of people who have been trained up
in more of a postmodernist camp we're
actually very uncomfortable with any
certainties even relative ones and it's
you know the assumption that all
certainties probably imperialism it's
probably someone gonna try and force
they're not Universal proof as if it was
Universal under the name of science on
everybody or something like that
but there's a lot we can say with pretty
high certainty about the molecular
properties of water there really just is
or the speed of sound or a lot a lot of
things that are pretty well-established
they're very useful and it's like you
know like Dawkins says here rightly
planes actually work whether you believe
in them or not and there's a there is a
reality to the mechanisms in those
domains so it's important to be not only
able to have certainty where it's
warranted but to seek it to seek
basically better and better
understanding of reality to inform more
responsible choice making but in order
to do that I've got to ignore I've got
to admit and acknowledge and be
comfortable with the amount of
uncertainty that's there so that I can
assess where I'm currently at and what
the appropriate process to come to
enough certainty to act is so I see that
same weird certainty on both the
conspiracy theorists and the anti
conspiracy theorists like there's this
in-group thing where one is it would be
so bad for my in-group if I was part of
the critical thinking anti conspiracy
camp and I started saying you know maybe
there really is such and such that
there's pretty strong incentives other
than just clear thinking against it
there's also other kinds of cognitive
biases that we can talk about that are
actually pretty important aliens I don't
fuckin know that I have seen some
evidence that I find quite compelling of
some things I have seen enough video
evidence of objects moving and
particularly declassified military stuff
not just the recent tik-tok but lots of
things
that do acute angles at speed which
doesn't go along with the nurse as we
understand it maybe it's just a hologram
which would make sense right because the
hologram can do that or maybe it's a
plasma being moved around by e/m field
or something or some kind of directed
energy weapon thing maybe it is some
kind of physical ship maybe I don't know
but it when you look at something like
the disclosure project and all of the
military officials very senior rear
Admirals and four-star generals and
whatever they came forward and described
the experience that they had with
unidentified objects objects that they
couldn't identify is that compelling
yeah it's totally compelling for me that
there is that many of them describing
some kinds of phenomena does that mean I
get to jump to knowing what the
phenomena are nope does that mean there
are aliens or there aren't aliens I
don't know but I I neither feel
comfortable saying I for sure have a
clear sense that it is or I can for sure
rule it out I can say that a lot of
people who understand how to read radar
and who understand as fighter pilots or
astronauts or whatever how to identify
the types of man-made objects in the sky
have seen a lot of things they can't
identify did seem earnest as opposed to
just lay dumb people so that's totally
fascinating for me but I'm comfortable
enough with uncertainty to leave it at
fascinating and say if I could figure
out where I would
do I think that there are people that
are airing on the side of unfounded
conspiracy theories and more of them
together and with more certain teams yes
definitely do I think there are also
other people airing on the side of being
comfortable with more authoritarianism
like the exact opposite side it totally
shouldn't be that are actually under
paranoid about what the true authorities
are telling them and how they will
handle things yeah I totally think that
both of those are happening nearly
equally and equally concerning lis no
I'm actually more concerned by the
second one honestly I think that there's
a problem with people saying that they
think that there isn't really a virus
they can absolutely fuck up endemic up
of that belief but I think the other
people who call for national security
actions to solve this that leave
authority states also creates a problem
that could be worse than the virus I
think there's another reason that people
are kind of having that increasing sense
is that there are a lot of increasing
authoritarian measures happening which
is legitimately concerning and should be
for anyone who has paid attention to
history and I think a lot of people do
have the awareness that even if
something wasn't intended as a grand
plot that opportunism is a thing and I
don't think that most people think that
Facebook and Google want everyone's data
for their good you know for everyone's
good like they they commercialize the
fuck out of that data in ways that do
not necessarily improve the lives of the
people and sometimes like like they're
actually turning the people into a
commodity the other thing is that when
you see developing nations respond
better than the US which has happened
for a number of them and when you see
mmm
when you see Vietnam responding better
right and
some Latin American countries and
whatever and you see how far ahead we
knew this was a thing and you see the
intelligence briefings that were there
and the lack of response and you know
what the logistical capabilities of the
of the US military and DOD that wouldn't
even have to override anyone's freedom
to just offer logistical support our and
you know how much damage is happening to
the economy and how much cheaper it
would have been to actually do upfront
work and the fact that there weren't
tests and that by the time we had got
our first hundred thousand tests out
Germany had been doing five hundred
thousand a week for a long time with a
tiny percentage of population there's so
much of that that a lot of people are
like is that just incompetence like it's
almost mind-blowing to imagine that
that's just incompetence given that we
have so much actual fucking competence
like the if there's anything the US
military is really good at like it's
really good at logistics and it doesn't
have to be deployed in a way that
overrides any civil liberties to simply
be deployed to support stuff to support
supply chains and get PPE where it's
supposed to go and shit why wasn't that
why didn't happen why didn't we get you
know and when you look at Germany and
its testing or you look at Hong Kong and
the way it shut the borders down you
look at the way South Korea rolled it
out as a democracy or you look at the
way Iceland did you look at this and so
and then when you also look at well why
the fuck did Beijing not let anyone fly
from Wuhan to the rest of China but they
did let them fly from wander the rest of
the world and a number of other very
strange things about the flows of PPE
and stuff like that I think that people
will jump to the wrong theory but
sometimes because of a right intuition
and the right intuition is there are
some agents benefiting from this and I
don't feel good about it
and then a rather than being able to sit
with the uncertainty long enough to do
the right kind of research so like did
Trump get this wrong for a long time in
terms of saying oh there's no big deal
we got it handled whatever yes totally
does that mean he's driving the whole
thing for some agenda for himself super
effectively and it's really because he
owns shares in the hydroxychloroquine
company and that's why he said it well I
would say that that's not very good
conspiracy investigation the fact that
he owns some shares in a financial
services company I think it's like a
mutual fund or something we're doing
some shares in a company that produces
hydroxychloroquine which is a generic
which means that it doesn't have a
patent on and lots of companies can
produce it and there's not much money to
be made on it yeah like you don't do
really good conspiracies for like a few
bucks you you could have to you have to
do something better than that so that's
just like a follow the money trail but
not not that money trail right that just
doesn't look like a particular good
money trail so actually the main thing I
want with conspiracy theorist is that
they get better at it did they get
better at actually studying history and
settings physiology and being able to
actually check facts and follow
accounting records and you know go read
the doctrine of unrestricted warfare to
have some sense of what PLA and CCP
likely think the whole idea don't ever
explain my malice what can be explained
by incompetence that's also an important
rule like slow-moving stupid internally
friction filled bureaucracies like
that's a real thing and the fact that we
have a lot of systems that are super
ossified and are not good at sense
making and not agile in their response
like that's a real thing so you can
certainly ascribe a lot of stuff to that
where there are groups it seemed to have
good Intel and the agenda capacity to
act and took the wrong actions it's more
interested you still don't necessarily
know what the motive was and this is one
of the interesting things about like
motive is something that is outside of
the domain of the formal methods of
science which is why social science
called
soft science because I can't measure
your motive I can't do a third-person
measure and repetition on that measure
well but can't I measure your brain well
we don't really have perfect one-for-one
neural correlates right so I can observe
your action and then I have to try and
infer motive and belief and the
inference is a big step now maybe you
wrote an email I can find your email and
you express it or whatever so this is
where people have to be careful if they
actually want to try to do sense-making
well to just look at where did I make a
logical leap and what was my basis to
make that leap and how much how much of
a what are the different answers that it
could be here and let's run all of them
and then how do I say for this
particular premise how how would I
falsify this or verify this or if this
was true what other things would be true
that I can look for if this was false
what other things might be true that I
can look for there the certainty of this
is just a virus everybody's doing the
best they can the political party I
don't like is kind of at fault for the
bad response and fuck those guys but we
just need to band together and kind of
help our political party win this next
time and solve the virus and whatever
and in a national participation the
certainty of that or the certainty of we
know the cabal that is organizing this
whole thing for 5g mind control whatever
they're both comforting in a certain way
now the bias here that I find
interesting is there there's lots of
nuance so I'm gonna oversimplify but I
definitely see people that have a
towards or away from conspiracy bias
that corresponds with their general bias
of how they relate to authorities and
like I said I'm oversimplifying but the
oversimplification is a starting place
for me
and I'm gonna even postulate where this
comes from
but again not all the time this this is
a pattern that we can observe enough of
the time that it's interesting to look
at the reason I'm careful with saying
things like that is because when someone
over norms their patterns that's one of
the places that their sense making
becomes bad I have seen relatively often
people who generally think that
government bodies are kind of lame and
ossified whatever but mostly regulate in
the right interests you can largely
trust authorities the universities
mostly say true stuff whatever things
those people the generous authorities
also generally have a frame that things
are mostly getting better in the world
right now a lot less people have that
frame but in general that frame and
generally not always those people did
better in childhood like at school in
sports they're oftentimes their parents
were either more success or they did
better relative to them so they had this
experience that the system actually
works for me and that the authorities
are are actually trustworthy and I have
a good relationship with him and that
creates a kind of intuitive felt sense
so it's so kind of like the symbol
grounding felt sense where then even if
they're in another environment where
that's not true and it was true in the
little micro environment of their
childhood that's still the felt sense
and then they sometimes will keep that
forever or they have to be disabused of
it somewhat painfully at some point now
other people who have the general sense
that most authorities are probably
corrupt and probably abusing power and
that most institutions can't be trusted
and that people with less power can be
more trusted and that there is usually
some process of corruption that is
required for climbing power ladders
those people generally weren't very
successful at climbing the ladders early
and often times had authorities
that abused power or that were like
negative experience with them whether it
was parents or school or church or
whatever it was not always but I'm
giving an example of a kind of bias that
can occur which is a towards or against
Authority bias a kind of result that can
happen more likely to believe in
conspiracies that the authorities are
bad or more likely to reject that the
authorities are bad and they kind of
developmental environment that could
give rise to it there's other
developmental environments could give
rise to it and there's other biases
involved in conspiracy but just one
example of a developmental pathway as
far as the sentence making for the
ongoing covert situation goes another
principle that I'll share that I think
is helpful and it will help you notice
where you're it'll it'll help you make
sense better but it'll also I hope you
notice where your own biases are is if
you read something that seems compelling
on a particular idea like that immunity
is conferred or immunity isn't convert
try to find things that say the opposite
that also seem the best thought out
there are and see if you understand the
arguments well enough to be able to
parse the difference and if not don't
hold a strong view on the topic so hey
the only way to get through this is herd
immunity that's the way that respiratory
viruses work so we need to keep the
elderly inside let everybody else go
outside it'll be fine there won't be
that many deaths because it's really
mostly only for the elderly and
immunocompromised and the only way we
get through respiratory viruses is herd
immunity
we've all heard some epidemiologist or
pathologist or somebody say pretty
confidently that well are there some
viruses that we don't get hurt immunity
to and we just really try to do
everything we can to stop their
transmission yeah totally
which one is this we don't know yet
and does it seem like a meaningful
percentage of the people who get
infected don't produce antibodies is
there good evidence that people who are
showing cleared are getting reinfected
is that reinfected or is it a resurgence
or was it a false test does it seem like
in the studies coming out of China that
older people are producing 3 to 5x the
antibodies of younger people which seems
to be the opposite of what we'd expect
which makes us question what those
antibodies will do will they will they
protect against getting it again where
you won't get it at all will they
protect where you still get it but it's
less severe or might they actually prime
a more severe response that happens with
some things like thank-you fever given
that people who die are actually dying
of excessive immune response right
cytokine storm responses or that a lot
of evidence of that if the antibodies
are conferred how long will they last
and given the decay rate on them and how
much can we infer from other
coronaviruses about this which is a
novel one and you know you see different
virologists saying this is not mutating
anywhere near as fast as influenza and
doesn't have the same recombinant oriole
dynamics it's probably if we come up
with a vaccine or people get immune
it'll be against it'll be good and then
other ones saying no there's actually
reasons to think that there's going to
be a follow-up round at least one and
it'll probably be more pathogenic before
you decide which of those you believe
make sure that you study the dialectic
well enough and understand it well
enough that you can ground where you
land in it
that's and so as soon as you read
something compelling just go search for
the end to this and then see if you
really understand it I would say that is
one just immediate obvious rule of thumb
rebel wisdom was set up to make sense of
the world at a deep
level than the mainstream media it was
built for these times of crisis and
change which is why we want to do what
we can to meet the challenge of the
times more films and also for our rebel
wisdom members weekly sense-making calls
with our amazing interviewees and also
we're introducing the wisdom gym a place
to practice some of the skills that
we've talked about on the channel thanks
for watching and see you soon
[Music]